Today we're going to talk about banks, banking.
Before I start, I want just
to remind you that we have Hank
Greenberg coming on Wednesday.
And we talked about him in
a previous lecture, but he is
one of the most important capitalists, I think, in the
world.
The firm AIG, which was started by C.V. Starr, was
converted into the biggest insurance company in the world
by Hank Greenberg.
Over many years, the two of them ran AIG exclusively,
first Starr and then Greenberg.
And Greenberg produced a very innovative, innovative
insurance giant.
It didn't end well, but I
talked to him the other day.
He said he's going to talk
about the end, what he learned
from the experience.
Once again, no one can control everything that happens.
And random shocks affect all of our lives.
He remains a very important, he's
no longer at AIG, but he's
going to be.
Thank you.
I think AIG remains a
very important force in our society.
Now he's very much involved with philanthropy, and doing
things like lecturing young people, which he freely does
out of a sense of commitment.
So, I think he's a
committed person that has a moral
purpose.
That's why I asked him
to be one of our lecturers.
I took an offer from
the national bank, which is a
little bit too expensive.
But today, we're talking about banks, and I wanted to
outline of my lecture, I'm going to start with the
origins of banks, thousands of years ago.
Then I'll talk about the theory of banks, fractional
reserves and deposit insurance.
Then bank regulation.
Particularly, in light of the
world financial crisis, which is
an economic crisis.
which has changed the nature of regulation, changes that
will be with us for decades to come.
I'll talk about shadow banking, which is the new
banking sector that emerged and escaped regulation until
the crisis.
And then I'll talk at the
end a little bit about comparison
of financial crises in the past in various places around
the world to see how banks managed in those crises.
So, first thing I want to
say, this is a lecture about banks.
And that means traditional banks who take
deposits and lend money.
It's not about investment banks.
That's another lecture.
An investment bank, a pure investment bank, does not
accept deposits.
And it's most
The most characteristic thing is underwriting of securities.
So, that's a different lecture.
And I'm not talking about central banks in this lecture.
That's also a lecture on monetary policy.
Central banks are the government organizations that
manage the money supply of a country.
OK.
So, we're talking here about banks.
And I thought I should
start out by defining a bank.
The word bank, by the way, means counter or tabletop,
where bankers used to do their business.
That's the English word that emerged in the 15th century.
But banks, of course, precede that with other names.
What is it that is the characteristic of a bank?
It's the activity of banks.
I would say, maybe the most characteristic thing is that
banks earn spread income.
That is, they borrow at a
lower interest rate and lend it out
at a higher interest rate, and they make the difference.
Your deposit rate is lower than
the rate at which they charge
for the loans they make.
So, that's the spread income of a bank.
OK.
And then, the other aspect of
banks is that they borrow at a
lower rate than they lend.
So, that's the idea of a bank,
that you borrow at a lower rate
than you lend.
So, that might be considered the
core idea of a bank, that
you borrow at a lower rate than you lend.
But I'm not sure that that summarizes it either.
There's other aspects of banks that we'll talk about.
Another aspect of banks, traditionally, has been note
that they print money.
That is, they print paper money, and then it circulates
and goes, you have some of these in your pocket.
They're currency.
If you stopped a person on
the street a couple hundred years
ago and said, what is the essence of a bank?
I suspect the first thing they
would say is, oh, they print
money, and that's the paper money that we use.
You don't think of it this way.
Probably not, because most of that function all over the
world has been shifted to the government banks, the central
banks in the various countries.
And so, you don't think
of private banks as issuing bank
notes.
But they used to, and it used to be prominent.
The private bank issuing of notes
today in the world is a
bank that I believe is concentrated primarily in two
countries.
One of them is the United
Kingdom, and the other one is
Hong Kong.
Tell me if there's another country.
I don't know who else does it.
In the United Kingdom, there are eight banks that still
print pound sterling notes.
And they're not very prominent.
In Scotland.
There are some.
I actually once went through the Channel from Scotland to
France, and I tried to spend
my Scottish sterling notes on the
train, and the guy who
was French speaking stared at it
and said, what's this?
And he wouldn't take it.
So, I said, this is pound sterling.
This is official.
This trades at par with the Bank of England notes.
Hong Kong has three banks that issue their bank notes.
The Hong Kong and Shanghai Bank Corporation, the Standard
Charter Bank, and the Bank of China Hong Kong.
Everywhere else, banks don't issue notes.
And the reason they don't is
laws have been made to prevent
them, because these notes lost value so many times in
financial crises.
And the government said, it's not something that will allow
private banks to do.
So, it's generally gone.
If you look at your $1 bills
in your pocket, it will give the
name of a Federal Reserve Bank.
And there's 12 of them.
Our Federal Reserve Bank here
is the Federal Reserve Bank of
Boston.
So, you can look at your
dollar bills and see which bank issued
it.
So, you're probably carrying a lot of Boston money.
But. . .
Since it's all the government, you don't even notice that,
right?
You don't notice.
If this were 1750 and you
had Boston money in your pocket,
you might, because we're in Connecticut, you might have a
problem.
You'd have to go to a
money dealer and have it exchanged,
because they didn't know or trust the Boston bank.
That's all past.
So, note issue is a matter of history.
So, there's other aspects of
a bank I want to emphasize.
One is. . .
liquidity.
And this is an essential element of banking as well.
And I'll come back to that
when we talk about theory in a
minute.
But banks offer liquidity by
borrowing short and lending long.
This is different from spread income.
I'm saying the interest rate is
lower on the borrowing of the
bank than the lending of the bank.
The interest rate is lower on the borrowing
of the bank than the lending of the bank.
There's another discrepancy.
The maturity is longer on the lending of
the bank than the borrowing of the bank.
So, banks are providers of liquidity.
That means a business wants to borrow money.
Or let's say a homeowner wants
to borrow money to buy a home.
Right?
Let's take that example.
That's more familiar.
You're going to lock up
the money for maybe 30 years.
You don't want to pay the loan back tomorrow.
What if the lender says, I
need the money, give it back?
You can't give it back.
You don't want to give it back.
So, what a bank does is it takes
deposits and allows people to cash them in whenever
they want.
It lends the money out
long on 30-year or so loans.
So, it generates liquidity.
The borrower has what he or
she wants, which is a 30-year loan.
The lender has what they want.
They have a loan.
They have an account they can get at any time.
But the problem with it – so, this is
an important function of banks – but the problem
with it is that there's a problem of crises.
Because, if everybody asks to pull their
money out at once, they can't do it.
The banks, in normal circumstances, generate
liquidity, but they create a system that's
vulnerable.
And so, the banking industry has been plagued by frequent
crises throughout history.
So, I wanted to say something about the very
beginnings of banking.
Who did it first?
Well, by the way, I should have written the word
interest rate.
When I'm talking about spread income or margin, I'm talking
about the difference between two interest rates.
But more primitive is the idea of interest rate.
So, where did that idea come from?
Well, I was reading some economic historians.
Apparently, the word interest first appeared in the Sumerian
language.
I guess the oldest records are about 2000 BC.
And they had a word, which
I don't know if you've ever
heard of.
They write as M-A-S, I guess that's pronounced mosh, which
was their word for interest.
But it also means lamb.
And so, one historian was wondering, why do the
Sumerians use the same word for
interest as they do for an
animal, a lamb?
And he thought that maybe it
was because the idea of lending
money at interest grew out of
an earlier idea of renting land.
So, you would have land
that you weren't using in ancient
Sumeria, and you would rent it
out to somebody who would then
use it.
One of the things that the
person would do with it is
graze livestock, graze sheep on the land.
So, you would say, well, I
need some produce from the land to
compensate me for letting you use it.
So, the guy would say,
fine, I'll give you all the
offspring of our sheep, the lambs.
That was an old tradition in Sumeria.
So, they thought, it's been a long time.
So, they were basically the same thing.
It's like giving over the lambs.
If I lend you money, I'm giving you productive resources.
And it's going to produce something.
We'll call it lambs.
And I want that.
And he's compensating me for it.
So, that's where the idea began.
And so, you'll find it in
the ancient world, in the near
non-Oriental ancient world, in ancient Greece and Rome.
Interest was well established.
And some kind of banking.
Now, I don't know whether
there were bankers in Sumeria, but
there probably were.
Because all it takes is that you do both sides.
You know, if you're lending money, actually, they didn't
necessarily lend money in those days.
They would lend barley or wheat.
And they would charge interest in terms of wheat.
You don't need money to do banking.
But I suspect that somebody
in ancient Sumeria, I don't know,
would have a good interest in that.
I don't know.
It's a big deal.
But anyway, what about these kinds of institutions that we
call banks?
Oh, also, the first, apparently, if I've got my
history right, the first record
of interest rates in China was
Song Dynasty.
The first record of interest
rates in China was the Song
Dynasty.
And that was from the year 960 to 1279.
They were, at that point, inventing paper money and
other financial institutions.
I don't know if they had institutions called banks,
but it often would be a family business lending money.
If you were a prominent family, you would often take
other people's money for safekeeping.
It was also connected with religious temples in the past.
But the modern banks seem
to appear in Italy in Renaissance
times, where they actually had a banking institution.
And that's where the oldest
bank in the world today exists.
It's in Italy.
It's called Banca Monte dei Dei Pasi in Siena.
And that means the bank of the mountain of sheep.
It's the same analogy, I guess.
I don't think they called their interest lambs.
And so, that bank was set up in 1470.
That's the oldest surviving bank in the world.
I went there.
You can go there if you visit Siena.
And they have a little museum
on the first floor near the lobby.
And it's actually the third largest bank in Italy.
Very old institution.
It's interesting that this bank, which was
founded in 1472, was founded as a philanthropic
institution to lend money to the poor.
And so, it's a very interesting institution.
And wealthy donors in Italy gave
money to set up this bank.
It goes beyond that now.
It's not just lending to the poor.
The other thing is, in the
1600s, they gave it deposit insurance.
Believe it or not, the Duke of
Siena said he would guarantee all deposits.
So deposit insurance appears to have
been invented in Italy as well.
How about the bank?
I don't know.
But a lot of people emphasize, when they
talk about the history of banking, I was reading,
preparing for this, economic histories, to
see what they would say about banking.
And Professor Clive Day, a professor here at
Yale, wrote a book called History of Commerce
in 1907.
You can pick up his book.
I had great fun reading it.
He's long gone, a professor at Yale.
But his history begins in England with the so-called
goldsmith bankers.
What happened was, in England,
in the maybe 1500s or 1600s,
somewhere around that time, goldsmiths who made gold
jewelry had safes, good places to store gold.
And so people would go to
the goldsmith, and maybe they were
having jewelry made, but then they'd say, could you keep
some of my gold in your vault?
And so the goldsmith banker
would say, all right, I'll do
that, and I'll give you a
note saying, I'll promise to pay
you this amount of gold that's in my vault.
So sometime when you're out shopping, the goldsmith
banker's note would say, here's a note for you.
It's in your pocket still.
And you want to buy something.
So you'd say, well, I've got this gold.
You talk to the merchant, and
you say, I've got this gold
that's in the goldsmith.
I've got his note here.
So the merchant would say,
all right, I'll take that, but
you've got to endorse it over to me.
Write a note on the note
saying that this thing is being
transferred to me.
And so I can go to
the goldsmith and get it out.
And that's how paper money got started in England.
It started to circulate.
And it was a very successful business.
It was a very successful business with many
endorsements on it.
And then finally, the goldsmith said, well, let's
forget about endorsing it to one person.
Let's just say it to the bearer.
And so the paper money started developing kind of
spontaneously.
And then the goldsmiths noticed, they've got all this
gold in their vault.
They can lend it out.
Why not?
Because nobody ever comes and asks for it.
Now that these paper notes
are circulating, nobody asks for it.
So I'll start lending it out.
And so they're sending out paper notes, because people
would hold them anyway, just because they
valued the safekeeping.
I guess they were paying interest in the sense that
they were providing the safekeeping.
So that's how banking got started in England.
But it was really preceded in Italy.
What has happened is,
Because of repeated problems in the banking industry, which
gradually grew through time into something that's more and
more important, governments all over the world regulate
them, and that means they define certain specific types
of banks that differ a little bit from one
country to another.
And when you decide to create
a bank, you have to decide
which type you are.
So I wanted to start, and
your textbook, Fibozzi, talks a lot
about types of banks.
But let me just talk about the major types.
I'll talk in the U.S. The
most important type of bank is
called a commercial bank.
And these are banks that take deposits.
You can buy them.
You can put your money in the
bank, and then it will pay you
interest, and it will also make loans of various kinds,
but most characteristically, business loans.
Commercial banks were even more prominent 100 or 200
years ago, because they didn't
do mortgages and consumer loans
back then.
It was all business loans initially.
So this is kind of
the historic important kind of bank.
And in 2010,
the total assets of U.S.-located commercial banks
was $14.6 trillion.
But actually, a lot of that was foreign commercial banks
operating in the United States.
Of that $14.6 trillion, only 10.1 was U.S.-charted banks.
So bankers operating in the United States, they were
operating in the United States.
So, the bankers operating in the United States, they were
They were operating all over the world.
So we have banks like, I mentioned, Hong Kong and
Shanghai Bank Corporation, or the various Swiss banks that
have big operations, or Deutsche Bank, big
operations in the United States.
So they account for almost
a third of our commercial banks.
But then there are other
kinds of banks, and they're smaller
in terms of, this is assets of the banks.
It's not their market cap.
The market cap would be much lower.
Because remember, offsetting these assets are liabilities.
They owe to the depositors.
But there's other kinds of banks.
There are savings banks.
In the U.S., savings banks had only $1.2 trillion.
So, that's a lot.
These savings banks were generally, they tend to be old
institutions that have grown very large over time.
They're the result of a savings bank movement in the
19th century, which was a philanthropic movement to set
up banks for lower income people.
Because commercial banks traditionally wouldn't take
deposits from small, you'd have to have a minimum size.
They didn't care about, they
didn't deal with ordinary people.
They didn't care about the money.
They didn't deal with ordinary people.
So, they created savings banks
to encourage thrift and saving.
Actually, it follows on a U.K.
movement, savings bank movement in the U.K.
And they're still with us, but they're not so big.
And there's also credit unions.
That's another social movement.
And they're only .9 trillion,
or about 900 billion in assets.
Credit unions are basically clubs of people that belong
together in some group.
So, if you have a company, you
can set up a credit union for
the employees of your company.
Both savings banks and credit unions
make a lot of mortgage loan.
That's kind of their characteristic business.
In U.K., you have the same kinds of banks.
The savings banks makeenda достаточно height.
And the savings banks would
be called building societies, but
it's the same idea.
They make loans for buildings.
OK.
So, I said I would
talk about the theory of banks.
I've already given you some indication by describing what
is it that banks do.
But I see I have a lot
more to talk about than I have to
consider my time here.
There's so much to say about banks.
It's a whole fascinating subject.
But I wanted to mention, the
theory of banks was laid out
in the Diamond-Dibvig model in the Journal of Political
Economy.
It was in 1988.
They were both colleagues of ours at Yale.
They've moved on.
So, I know them both, Doug Diamond and Phil Dibvig.
But what they described is a model.
I'm not going to give you
the model, just to tell you about
it.
A theoretical model of banks as providers of liquidity.
Liquidity is an economic good
that you can somehow get for
nothing.
It comes out of, well, it's just like portfolio
diversification.
We don't have to expend any resources to get
We just have to manage our portfolios right.
Similarly, you set up a
bank, and lo and behold, liquidity
appears.
And it makes it possible
for people to live their lives
better.
I mentioned, you can live in a
house for 30 years, or you can
move whenever you want.
But the problem with this is that there are multiple
equilibria.
Their model has a good equilibrium, and a bad
equilibrium.
And it depends on expectations.
If people think that the
banking system is sound and is
going to work well, it works splendidly.
But the problem is, all
it takes is for people to
suddenly change their expectations.
And then it falls apart, because you have a run.
You have a bank run.
So, what Diamond and Dibvig
did is to provide an economic
rationale for deposit insurance.
It's a simple thing.
It's a system, an insurance system, an insurance system
that's going to help people.
And the system, ensuring deposits against the default of
the bank helps people, helps prevent bad outcomes, keeps us
in the right equilibrium.
So, this is an important paper.
The problem is that bank
runs can be triggered by random
transactions.
What happened in the latest
crisis is, there was a real
estate bubble.
It's not something that's represented in Diamond and
Dibvig.
And the bubble, when it burst, when home prices started
falling, and commercial real estate prices started falling,
the banking system started to fall apart.
So, it's not entirely easy
to keep banks under good balance.
to keep banks under good control.
Now, I wanted to talk
about other aspects of banks besides
– you see, Diamond and
Dibvig emphasize that banks are an
invention that creates liquidity.
And liquidity is a positive economic good that makes us
run our lives better.
And so, it's an important
invention in the history of economics.
But there's other issues that banks do, problems they solve.
One of them is an adverse selection.
And the other one is
the risk reduction problem that plagues
securities.
I didn't mention the alternative
to banks for raising money, if
you're a business, is that
you could issue bonds or commercial
paper.
You can borrow money directly from the public without an
intermediary.
I'm a company.
I need money to, say, build a new factory.
I go not to a commercial bank.
I go to an investment bank.
And they help me issue some paper to the public.
And we sell it off in some market.
The problem with issuing debt
directly to the public is that
the public can't judge the quality of the company easily.
Right?
And the people who are investors are not
good at estimating the value of the security of
a company.
So, they need some kind of experts.
If the adverse selection would happen, see,
the experts, the people who know, would buy
all the good stuff.
And it would leave beyond, people would start
to think, I'm not going to buy these securities
because why are they being offered to me?
I don't know anything.
I'm a sucker.
That's the idea.
I'm not a sucker.
I don't know.
I may be smart, but I just don't
know what the quality of this company is.
So, if I just go in there blindly and
pick up whatever seems to be out there, I'm going
to suffer an adverse selection.
I'm going to get the worst stuff, because
I'm not looking, I can't look, they're going
to dump the bad paper on me.
So, banks solve that by being in the
community, knowing who is borrowing, and having a reputation,
so that instead of being a bad
person, they're going to be a good person.
So, that instead of you suffering this
adverse selection problem, the bank has people who
know what's going on.
So, the thing about banks is they have
local loan officers who serve in a particular community,
and they know all about that community,
and they solve the adverse selection problem.
So, for example, if you are a loan officer
in a bank, by tradition, you are someone who,
for example, gets involved in the community.
You'll find them on the program
at the symphony, among the donors.
They show up for all kinds of things.
They know what's going on.
They play golf with local business people.
They hear the gossip.
So, someone says, you know, this guy, CEO
of this company, I think he's an alcoholic.
You better watch this guy.
I don't know what he's doing.
You hear these things.
You know what happens?
The guy doesn't get a loan the next day.
I hate to say it, but they
kind of vouch for the character of people.
I mentioned this in a previous lecture, that there's all kinds
of people out there, and you can't prove or judge who's good.
You can't write it down in some objective
way, who's going to be a responsible business person.
But banks know that, so
they solve the adverse selection problem.
There's also a moral hazard problem.
The moral hazard is that
banks solve the adverse selection problem.
The moral hazard is that a company may borrow money
and then take a big flyer and do some wild investment.
Let's think this, for example.
Suppose we own a small
company, and it's not doing well.
We have this great idea.
Let's borrow $10 million, and let's go to the racetrack.
And let's put it all on the track.
Let's go to the racetrack.
And let's see who's the least likely horse to win.
And our chance of winning is only one of 10.
But if we win, I got $100 million.
If we lose, then hey, we just go bankrupt.
We say, sorry.
Of course, you really couldn't do it at the racetrack.
I mean, you'd be sued if you did that.
But you see what I'm saying?
I wouldn't do that.
But I could see wanting to do that.
Your company is going out of business anyway.
You're going to have to pay the debtors.
You're going to have to pay the prospects.
But if we can borrow $10
million, go and bet it on the
racetrack, and one in 10 will be super rich.
We'll have $90 million, right?
Pay off the debtors.
Everything's fine.
They won't complain if you win.
They'll complain if you lose.
But then you say, sorry, we're out of business.
So, it's limited liability.
So, what banks do is, they
help solve this problem by constant
monitoring, and they make commercial loans.
They keep renewing them,
but in practice, officially short-term.
They keep renewing them.
And they can cut you
off when they think you're doing
something that reflects moral hazard.
So, the constant monitoring that banks provide solves the
moral hazard problem, just as their information collection
solves the adverse selection problem.
So, okay.
I'm just trying to see
where I want to go next.
So, I mentioned deposit insurance.
I mentioned that it started in Italy in the 1600s.
But it has a long
history of governments backing up deposits
of banks in order to prevent bank runs.
Because bank runs happen too often.
People would get a little scare,
and they would go to the bank
and try to pull all their money out.
They'd hear a rumor.
And then the whole banking system would collapse.
So, people in various governments
at various times offered guarantees.
But the problem is, those
guarantees can get really expensive.
So, sometimes they had a limited guarantee.
And so, sometimes the deposit insurance scheme would fail.
And so, the history of
deposit insurance is a checkered one.
So, in the United States, there
were various state governments, local governments,
that created deposit insurance schemes before the FDIC.
But a lot of them failed.
And so, people said, this is a crazy idea.
But the United States government in 19, I
think it was 33, do I have this right?
Created, I'll put it, I think that's right.
The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation,
as part of the New Deal,
has never failed under Franklin Delano Roosevelt.
And it has never failed to this date.
Why didn't it fail?
I think, it's hard to know exactly.
We never had a big bank run since 1933.
It seemed to create the psychology
that people stopped worrying about bank failures.
Because they thought, they believed they were insured.
I guess they believed Franklin Delano Roosevelt.
So, if you believe it, then,
it's one of those funny things.
It's the multiple equilibrium
that Diamond Dibvick mentioned.
As long as people believe the
bank system is sound, it is sound.
But we did have a, we
also created later another deposit insurance
called the Federal Saving and Loan Insurance Corporation.
That was doing the saving and loan
associations, which were a type of saving bank.
And,
that did fail.
And so, we had a
huge crisis in the United States,
called the saving and loan crisis in the 1980s.
So, the S&L crisis
in the 1980s
was
due to a widespread failure of saving and loan associations.
And then, kind of a
run on the saving and loan.
But, it wasn't really a
run, because the FSLIC was trusted.
And what ended up happening is, the FSLIC had reserves
against a certain amount of losses from the banks.
But they went through them completely.
And then, they were bankrupt.
So, the insurer went bankrupt.
What then happened is, the United
States government picked up the tab.
And the total tab was
$150 billion.
So,
and that restored confidence.
I guess the government had to do that.
So, what you really,
and the FSLIC no longer exists.
Savings and loans are now insured
by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.
So, what, you know, these institutions
really don't necessarily represent the real insurance.
You have to always see beyond institutions.
The FSLIC was
encouraging people to believe in
the security of the banking system.
But it really wasn't the ultimate security.
The ultimate security wasn't even written down.
It was the recognition by the U.S. government
that if we let FSLIC fail,
and we let all these depositors in
the savings and loans lose their money,
it's going to destroy the confidence that
has kept us away from bank runs.
And the next thing, the commercial banks,
or who knows, what else will happen.
So, what always happens is
the government stands behind these promises,
even if they weren't made so clearly.
There's another example
I'll give you, which is more recent
of a bank run.
And that occurred in the United Kingdom
in 2007.
The bank was called Northern Rock.
And a rumor started,
this was at the beginning of the financial crisis,
the rumor started that Northern Rock
held a lot of subprime securities
and was going to go bankrupt.
So, people rushed to Northern Rock
and big lines formed outside of Northern Rock.
They wanted to get there first,
because you thought, well, they're
still handing out the money.
I want to be there first.
And then newspaper photographers photographed
the crowd outside the bank.
And people thought, well, this is just like 1933,
in the huge banking crisis.
And so,
now actually,
the UK government did have deposit insurance.
But the deposit insurance in the UK
would insure fully all deposits up to 3,000 pounds.
And then, it gave 90%
of the deposit insurance up to 75,000 pounds.
After that, you were out of luck.
Okay?
So, why was there a bank run on Northern Rock
when there was deposit insurance?
Well, I'll tell you.
It was people who had more
than 3,000 pounds in the bank.
Very simple.
And so,
you know, they didn't really have enough deposit insurance
to stop a run.
So, Mervyn King,
the head of the Bank of England,
just decided,
you know what?
We'll bail everybody out.
No questions.
Forget our deposit insurance scheme.
And that stopped the run.
So, again,
it happened the same way in the United Kingdom.
The deposit insurance
stopped it before
there was any problem.
So, the United Kingdom
has never had a bank run failure
since 1866.
And that's because,
it's not really because of any deposit insurance scheme.
It's about the Bank of England,
which is their central bank,
and what it does to maintain confidence.
Other countries handle it differently.
I was going to mention,
in Germany,
IKB,
Deutsche Industriebank.
Okay.
In 2007,
this is a German bank
that German depositors put their money in.
And it had invested a lot in subprime securities.
And it was in trouble.
And there was starting to be
worries of a run on them.
The German government didn't even wait
for a bank run.
They just bailed them out.
And that cost them
1.5 billion euros.
But again,
the governments know
that they want to maintain confidence.
And so, they do it.
They do what they have to do.
Now, I want to go to
bank regulation
more generally.
If you are insuring banks,
then you better regulate them.
Because there's a moral hazard problem.
I described a moral hazard problem
for a company that borrows money from a bank.
But there's moral hazard problems
for banks as well.
Namely,
banks can do the same trick.
I said,
go to the racetrack.
Borrow money and go to the racetrack.
Banks can do that.
Same thing.
I said,
they wouldn't actually go to the racetrack.
They would pick some really risky business venture.
And if it fails,
then it all falls to the deposit insurer.
This is a fundamental lesson of insurance.
Whenever you insure something,
you've got to regulate the person insured.
Because once you've taken a risk from their shoulders,
you create moral hazard for them.
And so,
bank regulation is very important.
So, I was going to talk mostly here about
the kind of bank regulation
that has an international dimension.
And so,
what I wanted to talk about is the Basel
bank regulations
that were generated by an international organization
in Basel, Switzerland.
After the saving of loan
crisis was the first Basel I
was an international meeting
that published a set of recommendations
for all the countries of the world
to regulate their banks.
The idea was that
there should be some coherence across countries.
If one country regulates its bank very stiffly,
that's going to drive business out of that country
into other countries.
Also,
there should be some standardization.
It helps the world economy
if everybody knows that all the banks of the world
have similar regulations.
But Basel,
the Basel committee,
as it's called,
that created the recommendations
had no legal authority.
All it could do is recommend.
But it did recommend bank regulations
and these were widely adopted around the world.
Each country could make modifications,
whatever they want.
You can't order countries around.
But they often followed the Basel recommendation.
In Basel II,
they met again in the 2000s
and they issued recommendations.
In 2004,
what they said in Basel II
was the banking system was getting
so much more complicated
that they had to think
more about how to do it.
Now there's all these complicated derivatives
and special purpose vehicles.
And so they had to update their regulation.
Unfortunately,
Basel II has suffered a reputation blow
because right after Basel II,
we had the world financial crisis.
So they didn't do something right.
They didn't really fix the system in Basel II.
So that brought us to Basel III,
which is the latest version.
And they issued their report in 2010.
And also in 2010,
the G20 nations meeting in Seoul, Korea,
expressed their support for Basel III.
So Basel III is the current world regulation standard.
But it's phased in gradually.
And it won't be fully phased in until 2019.
They didn't want to put it in all at once
because the world is in a financial crisis
and it would be too stressful.
So it has a slow phase in.
And
some of the details haven't even been worked out yet.
They've recommended,
the G20 countries have agreed in principle
that these regulations are where we'll go.
But details have yet to be worked out.
But I wanted to,
you know, bank regulation is a big business.
We could spend,
we could have a whole semester
studying what these guys do.
So I just wanted to give
you a kind of a caricature
of what's in Basel.
It's also in Fibozzi.
The Fibozzi textbook,
which is copyright 2010,
you'd think this would be in it,
but it's not.
Basel I and Basel II are in Fibozzi.
Basel III isn't because it didn't come in
until the end of 2010.
And so the book was,
it didn't make it in time
to appear in your book.
But I wanted to just give you a,
just a simple account of
all the Basel agreements.
And some sense of where we are with Basel III.
They're all about banks having enough money.
You know, not taking on too much,
enough money for the risks they take.
Let me start with Basel I.
And because part of Basel I
is enforced in all three of them.
And there's a concept called risk weighted risk.
And that's the risk weighted asset,
which is in Basel I.
And Basel II and Basel III,
essentially the same.
Okay, so here's the idea.
We're going to put capital requirements
based on risk weighted asset.
And what does that mean?
That means that banks cannot take too many risks.
They have to have enough money
to back them up for the risks they take.
And we'll call that money capital.
Okay, it's not money, it's not cash,
but it's assets that they can use
to get them out of trouble
if the risky assets do badly.
So if we're going to make,
we're going to have a requirement
on how much capital a bank holds.
We have also to define their risks.
And so Basel I had a very simple
formula to compute risk weighted assets.
Well, it's very simple
until you get into all the details.
And so you'll see the definition
of risk weighted assets.
It's in table 3.3 in Fibozzi.
But basically, here it is.
There's four categories of assets.
The 0% weight, the 20% weight,
the 50% weight and the 100% weight.
The higher the weight,
it means more risky.
Okay?
So where will I write these?
I'll do it up here.
Now, we're talking about all three,
Basel I, II and III.
0% are national,
well, I'll say OECD government bonds,
national government bonds.
The OECD is the
Organization for European Cooperation and Development.
And they represent advanced, stable European countries.
And U.S. government bonds
are included among them.
Okay.
What else?
It's basically this.
Those are the,
yeah, basically that's it.
Now, there might be something else in there.
And I'm sure there is.
But this is the simplest.
0% rate, because these have 0% risk.
There's no risk.
Okay?
So, banks can hold all they want of these,
and they don't have to hold any capital.
Then, next up is 20% weight.
And that's municipal bonds.
Now, or local bonds.
That's not issued by the national governments,
but issued by a city or a state.
We're having a municipal bond crisis now.
They're suddenly showing their risk.
And we're worried about defaults on them.
So, Basel I was right to give them some weight.
They gave them a 20% weight, because they thought
municipal bonds are pretty safe.
They're not as safe as national government bonds,
because there's examples of defaults.
But they also included,
there's a long list of what they include,
but notably, Fannie and Freddie.
Where,
these are the two mortgage lenders in the United States,
were included for 20% weight.
Because people thought, these guys
are really safe in any way.
The U.S. government backs them up.
Although the U.S. government said it wouldn't back them up.
But you know, we all know
they're going to back them up.
And indeed, they did back them up when they failed.
But Fannie and Freddie, prior to the crisis,
started increasingly investing in subprime mortgages.
And they were issuing subprime mortgage securities
that were really very risky, and eventually went kaput.
Basel I didn't know that.
Or Basel II and Basel III still,
they just give them a 20% weight.
It was a big mistake.
That's where part of the banking crisis comes.
Then there's 50% weight,
and that's for mortgages, home mortgages.
The Basel people thought,
there could be some big real estate crisis.
So, you know, it's something to worry about.
So, there's more weight than that.
And then we have 100% on everything else,
but notably loans, like commercial loans to businesses.
All right.
So, those are the weights.
And so, I just wanted
to go through a simple example.
Suppose you are a bank.
And you have $400 million in assets
on your balance sheet, okay?
These are things that you as a bank own.
And let's say you have 100 in government bonds,
federal government bonds,
100 in Fannie Mae,
100 million.
And you have 100 in mortgages
that you own directly.
And you have 100,
and 100 in commercial loans.
So, your total assets are 400 million.
But you got to know what your risk-weighted assets are.
So, what are your risk-weighted assets?
Well, I take the 100.
Fibozzi goes through an example too,
but this is very easy.
I multiply the 100 by zero, I get zero.
I multiply this 100 by 20%.
It gives me 20 million, right?
I multiply the mortgages by 50%.
It gives me 50 million.
And I got to throw all these in.
So, what does that add up to?
It's 170 million.
RWA, risk-weighted assets.
Right?
It's 20, zero plus 20 plus 50 plus 100.
All right?
So, those are my risk-weighted assets.
And then, the amount of
capital that I have to hold
is a percentage of the risk-weighted assets.
I don't want to go through,
I could go through Basel I, Basel II, Basel III.
They kept changing these percentages
and it's, as they went along.
So, I'm just going to talk about Basel III,
because that's going forward.
All right?
So, Basel, and Basel III is complicated too.
I'm going to just talk to you about
common equity requirements.
So, Basel III says,
and it's an interesting and creative construct.
Common equity must be 4.5% of RWA at all times.
But, I'm going to go through this.
But, I'll add to that.
They have plus 2.5%,
which they call capital conservation buffer.
And so, that adds up to 7%.
I'll explain.
You absolutely have to have 4.5%.
That's common equity.
But, if you don't also have another 2.5%,
you can't pay out any dividends.
That's not so good.
So, in reality, you better keep 7%.
So, effectively, Basel III,
this is Basel III.
Not in your textbook,
but it's coming all over the world.
Now, incidentally, the interesting thing about Basel III,
they're thinking creatively.
They added another buffer
called the counter-cyclical buffer.
Well, that's not added automatically.
And that's another 2.5%.
But, only if the regulators in
the country choose to impose it.
And here's the idea.
We have to stop bubbles before they burst, right?
So, suppose you think that a
bubble is building up in your country.
Then, the regulators are asked by Basel,
if they make that judgment,
to add another 2.5% to the capital requirement.
While it's booming.
You do this while it's,
you don't wait until the crisis to do this,
because then they'll all be in trouble.
And if you tighten up on banks then,
they'll stop making loans.
And they'll trash the whole economy.
You gotta tighten up when times are good.
So, that adds up to 9.5%.
Okay, so you'd have to hold capital equal to 9.5%
of your risk-weighted assets.
But presumably, the normal number is 7%.
Okay, so let me just
go through for this bank here,
which has $400 million in assets.
What is their requirement?
Well, we figured out,
that they have $170 million in risk-weighted assets.
Multiply that by 7%.
And that gives you,
I think it's $11.9 million that they have.
Right?
So, your common equity must be $11.9 million.
So, you go to your balance sheet.
We showed balance sheets in an earlier session.
It's common equity plus the buffer,
plus the first buffer.
I'm sorry.
The 11.9 is the...
Oh, did I do that with...
Yeah, I'm sorry.
That's 7% of $170 million.
Yeah, it does have...
You don't actually have to do...
Yeah, you don't actually have to hold this buffer.
But it limits you if you don't.
And so, practically, most banks will.
So, then you go look on your balance sheet.
You see, hey, we're lucky.
We've got $12.9 million.
Let's say.
I just made that up.
All right.
How do you get common equity?
You take the total assets in your balance sheet.
You subtract off all of the liabilities,
all the money you owed.
And that gives you shareholders' equity.
But that has two components,
common equity and preferred equity.
So, you've got to subtract off the preferred equity.
But it's a sense of
how much extra resources you have
after you've paid off all your debts.
You still have $12.9 million.
So, that gives...
You say, hey, we're good.
We've got an extra million dollars.
Okay.
So, then you bring that up
at the board meeting and say,
we're satisfying Basel III.
Isn't that great?
But someone at the board might say,
but wait a minute.
That means we have a million dollars too much.
It's just sitting there.
We're not even using it.
Let's lend it out.
All right.
Let's...
Well, I'm sorry.
Let's use it up, not lend it out.
How do you use it up?
You use it up.
Now, you've got more than the amount of capital required.
You've got another million dollars.
You could lend out a million dollars.
But think about it.
You can borrow more and lend more.
You can make loans.
Or you can borrow more and take other assets.
And you can go beyond a million dollars.
So, here's what you can...
Let's consider this.
So, do you understand the
situation that we've done our accounting?
We have 170 million in risk-weighted assets.
We have a requirement, therefore,
of 11.9 million in common equity.
We have an extra million dollars.
Let's consider buying different kinds of assets.
How about buying Fannie Mae bonds?
All right.
Now, remember, you only...
How much more can you buy?
Well, you've got a million dollars.
If you're going to buy
more, you're going to add both.
You're going to borrow money,
and you're going to buy more.
So, you're going to add both
assets and liabilities to your balance sheet.
How far can you go to bring your...
So that you...
Without violating the capital requirement.
Well, what you can...
The amount you can buy of Fannie and Freddie
bonds is 1 million all over 0.2 times 0.07.
Right?
And that's about 70 million dollars.
So, you can buy a million bonds.
That's about 70 million dollars
worth of Fannie and Freddie bonds.
Because you add that to this mix, then it
will raise your risk-weighted assets by exactly 1 million dollars.
So, you can buy 70 million dollars of Fannie
and Freddie bonds, according to this risk-weighted asset calculation.
You see that?
Well, how about making loans
to small businesses in our community?
Well, that's 100% risk-weighting.
So, that means I can make
loans of 1 million all over 0.07.
And that's about 14 million.
So, this is what you
would tell at a board meeting.
And you're saying, let's consider that.
We're going to stay within the requirements.
We can buy 70 million of Fannie bonds,
or we can make 14 million more loans.
Well, at the board meeting, someone might say,
you know, 70 million sounds better than 14 million.
I think we should do Fannie bonds.
And tell all the guys with small businesses coming by,
tough luck, you know, we
don't have any money for you.
So, you see what it's doing.
It's pushing people.
The Basel requirement, and these were
Basel II or Basel I requirements,
were pushing banks toward investing in
subprime loans issued by Fannie Mae,
as against lending to businesses.
And people are starting to wonder about that now.
But you say, isn't the prosperity
of the country determined by the businesses?
Why are we lending?
When you're making a subprime
loan, what is a subprime loan?
It's a loan to someone with bad credit,
who has bad employment history, to buy a house.
So, we have created an incentive for banks
to lend to those people rather than to businesses.
And so, we're going to do that.
And so, there are critics of
Basel, all the Basel agreements, saying,
it's counterproductive.
We shouldn't have done this.
These weights were wrong.
There shouldn't have been so
little risk weighting on Fannie Mae.
But then the Basel people would say,
look, we can't get it exactly right.
We thought Fannie and Freddie,
and we're right, they haven't failed.
Our job at Basel is to
prevent a run on the banks.
So, we want banks to be sound.
And maybe you're right.
Maybe businesses should be encouraged,
but it's not our department.
We're trying to prevent bank failure.
So, these rules stick, and they're
still with us today under Basel III.
If you want to subsidize small
businesses, countries like in the United States,
we have the Small Business Administration
that gives loans to small businesses.
But it's not, Basel III
is not going to do that.
So, I said I would talk about it.
I'm going to talk about other financial crises.
And let me talk briefly about a few,
and then I'm going to have to wrap up.
The crisis that we have been through
was a worldwide crisis, starting in 2007,
peaking in 2008 and 2009.
And it caused a worldwide recession.
So, it's especially vivid in our memory.
But I want to just reflect that these crises,
we've had banking crises so many times in history,
that it's not a unique event.
And I just wanted to remind
ourselves of a few other crises.
I'm going to start with the
Mexican crisis, our neighbor to the south.
It was in 1995.
Under President Salinas, the
government privatized Mexican banks.
Salinas was a Harvard-educated economist who
wanted to modernize the Mexican economy.
And they privatized the government banks, and
turned it over to the free market.
And they forgot to regulate it.
And so, it led to a bank lending boom.
In 1988, lending was 10% of GDP.
1994, up to 40% of GDP.
Salinas did not stop this.
He thought this was...
And it led to a boom in Mexico.
Because lending was going wild,
everything was happening really fast.
And it led to a
bubble and a boom in Mexico.
And there should have been a
regulator who said, stop it anyway.
But there wasn't effective
regulation, because Mexico had deregulated,
but it hadn't set up
the banking institution, the regulatory institution.
So, they developed an atmosphere in Mexico.
That, you know, I don't worry about the possible
crisis, because the Mexican government will bail everybody out.
And, you know, they couldn't
bail everyone out, it turns out.
There was a collapse.
So, Salinas was replaced by Yale-educated Ernesto Zedillo.
I shouldn't put it that way.
And the Mexican banking system was destroyed by this crisis.
And what ended up happening is that most
Mexican banks were taken over by foreign banks.
And it was followed by an economy
that was heavily damaged by a crisis.
But Mexico recovered.
And 1994, 1995 was unique to that country.
It was a...
It was a terrible recession that hit Mexico briefly.
That's one example.
But again, it was a regulatory failure that did it.
If you allow the moral hazard to
develop, if you allow people to think that,
hey, let's make all these loans, I think
it will work out, but maybe it won't.
And if it doesn't, hey,
we have friends in Mexico City.
And so, we'll all be all right.
The next example is the Asian crisis.
And this was a very complicated
crisis involving a number of Asian countries.
But it was heavily related to bank lending.
And international banks had lent a
lot of money to Asian countries.
And the countries then had
loans that were dependent on them.
And they were dependent on loans that were
withdrawn when a sort of a bank run occurred.
It was something like a bank run.
Because the international investors suddenly wanted to
withdraw their money from the Asian countries.
And the Asian crisis started
in Thailand and Korea and Indonesia.
And then it spread all over the world.
It reached Russia as a consequence.
And it's called the Russian debt crisis.
It was a contagion effect.
And it got all the way down to Brazil.
You wonder why was Brazil affected by an Asian crisis.
Well, the world was and is interlinked.
So, it's experiences like this that
encourage people to think about the world.
And it's a very important thing.
Experiences like this that encourage the
G20 countries now agree on bank regulation.
That will prevent this kind of collapse.
And the last example I have.
Again, this one is not so international.
The Argentine crisis of 2002.
This was, again, a compliated crisis.
government shutting down the banking system in Argentina.
I don't have much time to talk about all this.
I guess let me just sum.
The examples that I gave
of crises around the world, I
went through them very quickly.
But let me just reiterate the
themes that I started out with
and that is that banks
fill a fundamental role in our
economy.
They make things work.
They solve moral hazard problems.
They solve adverse selection problems.
They create liquidity, so that businesses can function and
individuals can function.
When the crisis develops, we suddenly
realize the importance of our banking system in its absence
or in its poor behavior.
And so, I think there's an
attitude among a lot of people
that they don't like regulators, that they don't
appreciate regulators.
But in fact, regulators are
people who are managing a very
complicated system, which is really important to our
prosperity.
And so, I think that's the point.
Thank you.
If you look at causes of economic disruptions, it's
failures in our banking system that seem often to be
responsible.
There's other things, like for example, an oil crisis, that
seems to be completely independent of a banking
crisis.
But you take those two together, and you explain
most economic crises.
It's a very important thing to get banks regulated right.
Now, what I didn't talk about
in this lecture is, and I'm
going to come back to
this, is the shadow banking system.
Let me just mention this in anticipation.
And that refers to other kinds of companies, not officially
banks, that are doing business that resembles banking and is
not regulated.
So, for example, Lehman Brothers, or, you know, the
Lehman Brothers, or the Goldman Sachs, or the Goldman Sachs,
or the Goldman Sachs, or
the Goldman Sachs, or the Goldman
Sachs, or the Goldman Sachs,
or the Goldman Sachs, or Bear
Stearns, which were major failures that led to this
crisis.
They were not banks.
Well, they're not commercial banks.
They're not under Basel III.
They are investment banks, which is a different animal,
and it's not regulated by Basel III.
And so, what's happening as
we have, let me add, innovation
in finance.
I'm sorry.
Isn't that great?
Because it's making the financial world harder and
harder to understand.
That's why we keep having
Basel I, Basel II, Basel III.
There's going to be a Basel IV.
Financial systems are so much more complicated than they
were, say, in the 19th century.
There used to be a bank.
You can see, there's one downtown New Haven that looks
like a Greek temple.
You probably didn't even notice it.
I looked at the cornerstone.
It was 19th century.
You'd go in, and there'd be
a banker sitting there, and you
could talk to a person, and they'd make a loan.
But now, we have all these complicated derivative
contracts, and they trade all over the world.
It's so interconnected.
And shadow banking, which I'll come back to later, shadow
banking is a consequence of,
it's the kind of thing that
happens.
Regulators can't keep up with all these innovations.
But I don't think the
answer is to shut down innovation.
We just have to allocate resources, and that's a trend
that we are doing.
And I think that we
will benefit if we have effective
and sound regulation that takes into account the
subtleties of moral hazard, adverse selection, the
importance of liquidity.
These are basic, important concepts that make for better
lives for people.
And we have to expect
that regulation is going to get
through.
If we want to be
more selective, we have to have
a more complex regulation.
And we have to have a more complex regulation.
And we have to have
a more complex regulation that's going
to get even more complex.
Basel III may look complex,
it's going to get even more
complex, but we'll have computers managing the